Elizabeth Hale Niebyl papers M2243
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Elizabeth Hale Niebyl papers
1946-1982
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Niebyl, Elizabeth Hale
M2243
0.75 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Content Description
Materials include correspondence, published reports and proposals, printed pamphlets and brochures, as well as manuscript drafts of research adn memorandum, notes, and more. Topics covered include senior housing, veterans' housing, poor and middle class housing, rent control, evictions, housing prices, discrimination, and more.
Biographical / Historical
Elizabeth Hale Niebyl (1912-1984) was a leader in public housing during the New Deal era. She was married to Marxist economist Karl Niebyl (1906-1985). Elizabeth Niebyl worked as an information analyst for the U.S. Housing Authority in the 1940s, and worked as an officer at various housing authorities on the East Coast before moving to California with her husband in the 1970s.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by Stanford Libraries in 2017. Accession MSS 2017-192.
Discrimination in housing -- United States; Low-income housing -- United States; Housing authorities; Niebyl, Elizabeth Hale
- Using Census Data, Coleman Woodbury's remarks to the American Economic Association 1947 meeting on veterans housing and the use of census information; The 1950 Housing Situation in Charts booklet (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Survey of World War II Veterans and Dwelling Unit Vacancy and Occupancy in Asheville, N.C., Dept. of Commerce, Bureau of the Census, November 29, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Activities and Reports of the Southern Conference for Human Welfare, Ashville Chapter - handwritten and typed notes related to substandard housing and planning needs in Asheville, N.C., 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence on housing to and from Elizabeth Niebyl; notes/report, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- The Housing Situation in Plattsburgh, report co-authored by E. Niebyl, together with recommendations to the city government, 1950-10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Public Housing Administration, New Jersey, including two reports (Half-box 2, Folder 1)
- E.H.N. paper given before New Jersey State Planning 9/21/60. Sound Community Development and Rebuilding Aids Provided by State and Federal Governments, including handwritten notes (Box 1, Folder 5)
- San Jose and Santa Clara Rent Relief and Housing, three reports. Housing: a Call for Action; Racial Discrimination in Housing Audit and Recommendations, a report by the San Jose Housing Service Center; Draft of the Housing Element Problem Statement, a Background Report for the General Plan Revision Project, April 18, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Los Gatos Housing and Community Development, proposals, reports, grant proposal and other; newspaper clippings (1973-1975) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- National Housing Conference, Washington, D.C.: resolutions adopted, keynotes address by Leon N. Weiner, memorandums, legislative report, and other, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Santa Clara County Housing: Inter-city Council minutes, memorandums, sub-element draft. Many newspaper clippings regarding local rent and house price issues, 1974-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Many newspaper clippings regarding local rent and house price issues in Santa Clara County, 1974-1981 (Flat-box 3, Folder 1)
- Newspaper clippings related to Staten Island housing, 1956 (Flat-box 3, Folder 2)
- Critical housing need stressed on Congress, newspaper clipping, 1952-05 (Flat-box 3, Folder 2)
- Mahwah, New Jersey Volunteer Housing Committee correspondence, survey reports and two major reports authored by Elizabeth H. Niebyl, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Possible future research folder which includes various reports and other documents, on historic preservation, HIghland Park, NJ, college curriculum for housing, regional planning study, Lavanburg Homes, Twenty Years Record in Housing Pioneering, The New Mythology of Housing, etc., newspaper clipping (1956), 1956-1981 (Half-box 2)
- Senior citizen housing - reports and newspaper clippings (Half-box 2, Folder 3)
- Senior citizen housing - newspaper clippings, 1977 (Flat-box 3, Folder 2)
- Housing issues, California, including San Francisco: circulars, newspaper clippings and In historical perspective - is redevelopment of the Western Addition A-2 a ripoff?, 1970-1980 (Half-box 2, Folder 4)
- Housing issues, California, including San Francisco: newspaper clippings, 1970-1980 (Flat-box 3, Folder 2)
- Housing issues - national - newspaper clippings and reports, 1977-1982 (Half-box 2, Folder 5)
- Housing issues - national - newspaper clippings, 1976-1979 (Flat-box 3, Folder 3)